Hello everyone and
welcome back to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
I'm Erica and today we
have a great intermediate lesson for you.
That's right, we've got some excellent real
English for you all
about cleaning the house.
Cleaning the house,
that's a real life situation
so we're going to
give you real English.
Exactly. So in today's
lesson we're going to look
at language about cleaning the house. We're
also going to learn a few phrases that you
can use if you want to ask someone for help
and maybe if you're a little bit lazy like
me a phrase or two to avoid doing work.
Okay well let's get started then with our
vocabulary preview. Very cabaret-y preview.
All right great we have two great words
for you today. Erica why don't you
tell us the first one? The first word is
such a mess. So when
something is a mess it's dirty.
Yeah or things are
everywhere. Disorganize.
Yeah so you know you
have your clothes on
the floor and your shoes.
Okay so that sounds
a lot like my desk at
work. Your shoes on your
desk yeah I've seen
that. I've been wanting
to ask you about that. Okay
such a mess really really dirty.
Okay now let's take a look
at our second word. Chores.
Chores. Chores. Chores is a
really common word for things
you have to do around the house.
Like for example laundry or
making the bed or when you
have to take out the
garbage. Those are all
examples of chores.
Chores yeah I guess everyone
can remember when they were kids they had
chores to do. Yeah when I was a kid it was
my chore to chop wood. Yeah that's a great
chore playing with an axe. Maybe if you're
a boy but for a girl it was not so great.
Ah that's why you're so strong and fit. All
right so let's listen to our dialogue for
the first time. It's gonna be kind of fast.
But don't worry if you
miss something because
it will explain all of
the important language
afterwards. Honey the
house is such a mess.
I need you to help me
tidy up a bit. My boss
and her husband are coming over for dinner
and the house needs to be spotless. I'm in
the middle of something right now.
I'll be there in a second. This can't wait.
I need your help now.
Alright I'm coming.
Okay here's a list of
chores we need to get done.
I'll do the dishes and get
all the groceries for tonight.
You can sweep him up the floors.
Oh and the furniture
needs to be dusted.
You know what I have
to pick something up in
the mall so why don't you
clean the floors and I'll go to
the supermarket and get all
the groceries. Sure that's fine.
Here's the list of all the
things you need to get.
Don't forget anything and can you pick
up a bottle of wine on your way home?
Hey honey I'm back. Wow
the house looks really good.
Great can you
set the table? Just
a sec. I'm just going to
vacuum this rug wheel fast.
Wait don't turn it on.
So my god Marco what
happened there? An explosion.
We love a good explosion
here at English. We're
going to give you as many explosions as
possible. Okay so let's take a look at our
language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
So language takeaway is
the part of our lesson where
we teach you what
we think are some really
important words that
are found in the dialogue.
Exactly and we have three really important
words in our dialogue today. So let's start
with the first one. Tidy up. Tidy up. Tidy
up. So to tidy up means to put things in
their correct spot. Right.
So put the shoes on
the floor, and those
shoes off my desk. Exactly.
So tidy up. Organize
things a little bit.
Yeah put things away.
Okay let's take a look
at our second word
now. Spotless. Spotless.
Spotless. Spotless. So
when you want something
to be spotless, you
want it to be really clean.
Really clean. Not
a spot of dirt on it.
Like your desk. Exactly
my desk is spotless.
My desk is not spotless. All
right great word. Now let's
take a look at our last
word for language takeaway.
Mall. Mall. Mall. M-A-L-L. Mall.
It's a strange sounding word.
It is a little bit funny sounding but
it basically means a large building
with many shops inside,
many different stores inside.
Right. Now in British English you would
say shopping center. Yeah I think that's
a little bit more
common but in American
English we say mall.
Great. So now it's time
in our show to look
at putting it together.
Putting it together.
Okay so in putting it
together we take a word
from the dialogue and
we show you how to use
this word in real English.
So we give you a couple of examples
of how this particular word can be used.
Exactly so the word that we
have for today is groceries.
Groceries. Groceries.
Erica why don't you tell
us what groceries are
all about. So groceries
are all of the food items that you need to
buy at the supermarket so like your bread
and milk and meat and
vegetables. Exactly those
are all groceries.
Okay so let's listen to
some examples on
how we use this phrase.
Example 1. There's no milk.
Can you go to the grocery
store? Example 2.
Here's the grocery list.
I need all of these
things so that I can cook
dinner tonight.
Don't forget anything.
Example 3. I hate grocery
shopping. I can never
find what I'm looking
for. Okay great examples.
We heard some really
interesting combinations right?
Yeah we heard
grocery store which is
where you buy your
groceries. Exactly. Groceries
shopping. Buying
all your groceries.
And grocery list where you have
all the items that you need to buy.
A list of everything
you need to buy.
Exactly. You know grocery store.
I think this is quite a
common word in Canada.
Probably North America.
Yeah. Do you say grocery
store in America?
Well if it's a small one.
Really so like a small
store. In Canada I say
grocery store for even
like a supermarket.
Really? Yeah. I guess well
I would say supermarket
for a large one and grocery
store for a little corner shop.
All of these little differences
in American Canadian English. Okay I think
it's time for us to listen to our dialogue
another time. This time
it'll be a little bit slower.
Honey, the house is such a mess.
I need you to help
me tidy up a bit.
My boss and her husband
are coming over for dinner
and the house
needs to be spotless.
I'm in the middle of
something right now. I'll be there
in a second. This can't wait.
I need your help now. Alright,
alright. I'm coming. Okay.
Here's a list of chores
we need to get done.
I'll do the dishes and get
all the groceries for tonight.
You can sweep
and mop the floors.
Oh and the furniture
needs to be dusted.
You know what? I have to
pick something up at the mall.
So why don't you
clean the floors
and I'll go to the supermarket
and get all the groceries?
Sure that's fine.
Here is the list of all the
things you need to get.
Don't forget anything
and can you pick up a bottle
of wine on your way home? Hey honey
I'm back. Wow, the house looks really good.
Great. Can you set
the table? Just a sec.
I'm just going to
vacuum this rug real fast.
Wait. Don't turn it
on. Okay. Great stuff.
Love hearing that explosion
that vacuum just is a bomb.
Yeah. In this dialogue there was some
really interesting language that you can
use if you don't want to
do any chores in the house.
Exactly. So it's time
now for fluency builder.
Fluency builder. You know fluency builder
is a part of our show that we use to
take a common phrase
or a word that you
already know and show
you how to express that
idea more fluently and
more naturally. Exactly.
So let's take a look
at our first idea that
we want to explain. Let's say you're watching
TV like the woman in this dialogue and
your husband wants you to help him
do the chores and you say no I'm busy.
Right or I'm doing something.
Those are two great expressions
but we heard something
a little bit different
in the dialogue. I'm in the
middle of something right now.
I'm in the middle of
something right now.
Yeah that phrase is great.
It means she's busy.
She's doing something.
Yeah I'm in the middle of
something. Yeah. And so Marco you
can tell us about our
next phrase. Okay well now
suppose that you want
to say you'll be there soon.
You might say I'll be there
soon or I'm coming exactly.
But in our dialogue
we heard something a
little bit different.
Let's listen. I'll be there
in a second. I'll be
there in a second.
So this is a more natural way
of saying I'll be there very soon.
Yeah and you know
what I think I use
this phrase almost every
day. I'll be there in a second.
Yeah yeah it's really common.
Yeah it means I'll be there
really fast. Yes. Okay so
our final item today
in fluency builder is a
great phrase that
helps you say the idea.
Could you or would
you? Right or can you?
Yeah so can you sweep the
floor? Could you sweep the floor?
But in the dialogue we
heard something that's
a little bit different.
Why don't you clean the
floors and I'll go
to the supermarket.
Why don't you clean the floors
and I'll go to the supermarket?
Great so this is more natural
and it's giving a suggestion.
Yeah it's sort of a
polite way of asking
someone to clean the floors. Right it's
a really good and polite way of saying it.
Yeah I would agree on that.
This was fluency builder now we
are ready to listen to
our dialogue again at its
normal speed and this time
you'll understand a lot better.
Honey the house is such a mess I need you
to help me tidy up a bit. My boss and her
husband are coming over
for dinner and the house
needs to be spotless. I'm
in the middle of something
right now I'll be
there in a second.
This can't wait I need your
help now. Alright I'm coming.
Okay here's a list of
chores we need to get done.
I'll do the dishes and get
all the groceries for tonight.
You can sweep
them up the floors.
Oh and the furniture
needs to be dusted.
You know what I have to pick
something up in the mall so
why don't you clean
the floors and I'll go to
the supermarket and
get all the groceries.
Sure that's fine. Here's
the list of all the things
you need to get. Don't
forget anything and can you
pick up a bottle of
wine on your way home.
Hey honey I'm back. Wow
the house looks really good.
Great can you set the table? Just a sec
I'm just gonna vacuum this rug wheel fast.
Wait don't turn it on!
Um has this ever happened to you? Has
your vacuum cleaner exploded in your house?
Well not a big explosion like this one. Not
so dramatically and not so dramatically but
I've had this happen to
me before yeah and dust
everywhere and it's just
it's a mess you don't want to
have. You know this word vacuum
is really a very American word.
Yeah vacuum the
rug vacuum the carpet.
Yeah vacuum cleaner in
the UK what did they say?
Hoover. Hoover. Yeah
Hoover. Hoover the rug
Hoover the rug which
is interesting because it's
actually a brand. Yeah
so I guess it's kind of like
American English you
say past me a Kleenex.
Oh that's true. That
would be like a tissue.
Yeah so I guess they say Hoover
the rug or Hoover the house.
Wow you know I really love these small
differences and meaning that we have between
American English and
British English. It's fun okay
well another interesting thing about this
is that the man was doing the housework.
I know he's a house husband.
Yeah so he's the one doing all
the chores in the house.
Yeah that's well that's
the new trend now now
it's more popular for men
to stay home and take
care of the babies and
clean the house. Yeah
like when I was growing up
my dad would take out
the garbage and that was it.
My mom had to do everything else but
now I think it's becoming a lot more common
and especially in North
America for the household
chores to be divided between
the man and the wife equally.
Yeah I think it's fair. Me too.
Yeah you'd make a good husband
Markov. That's what they say
but they haven't married
me yet okay all right well
we're out of time folks
be sure to log on to our
community website
and you can leave all your
comments and maybe other
house husbands out there
can give us their feedback
on what they think about this.
Yeah so check us
out at EnglishPod.com
and thanks for listening
today everyone until next
time this is Marko and
Erica saying bye goodbye